Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 4 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory04
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 4 -- Letters to Franklin
1779 January-November
Mss.B.F85inventory04
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
1074 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Scope and Contents note
    The reply of the States-General to the memoir of France; in case they refuse to agree to France's terms, the King will exclude them from the regulations in favor of neutral nations. Sir Joseph Yorke's influence with a certain great personage. Splendid part played by their friend [M. Van Berkel].
    (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Arnold, ----- d’
    Has written to General Arnold to grant him, in consideration of the name he bears, employment in the American army; is thirty-eight years old and the father of a numerous family; desires Franklin to lend his influence to the request.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    The "Chasseur" loaded and only waiting for the "Governor Livingston," which is detained by contrary winds at Isle de Ré; glad a convoy is appointed. Continued advices of captures have stagnated all private expeditions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Chondeville, -----. Bourges
    Accusation against one M. le Ralle, who is probably in hiding at Paris, and who, among his other crimes, borrowed ten Louis from him which he never returned; thinks he may seek Franklin's protection, and so forewarns him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Marseilles
    The protection and assistance he rendered to Americans in Ireland, particularly Colonel Ethan Allen and those who were with him. Desires a license to remain in Marseilles with his two sons and their Swiss tutor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 3; L.S. John Jay, President. 2p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Transmitting an Act of Congress of the 23d ult.; quotes from the Secretary's letter to explain who Mr. Gosrunus Erkelens is and the nature of his occupation; encloses a copy of an Act of Congress of the 1st inst. on the subject of an expedition against Canada.
    (In triplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Enclosing a letter, received the day before, from Dr. Berkenbout; wishes to know if anything can be made of it for the public good.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 4; A.L.S. 1p.; D.S. 2p.; Hope and Co. Amsterdam
    Desired by Messrs. Jacob Hagen and Son, of London, to enclose the following copy of a Resolution of the Pennsylvania Land Co.
    Enclosure. A Resolution to propose to the Governors of the pennsylvania Hospital to receive from the Pennsylvania Land Co. as much of their remaining property in America as may be deemed a reasonable equivalent for the sum due them.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 4; A.L.S. Fra[nci]s Hopkinson. 1p.; The Treasurer of Loans. Philadelphia
    Notification of bills of exchange furnished to the Continental Loan Office of Massachusetts Bay.
    (In duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Theobald, James. London
    In his letter of November, 1777, acquainted Franklin with the death of Mrs. Bache, of Preston; is very anxious for news of Franklin and his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Du Bouchet, Denis-Jean-Florimond de Langlois de Mautheville, chevalier. Auxerre
    Wishing Franklin every happiness and prosperity. Desires any news he may have received of General Conway.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 4; L.S. 2p.; Calmels, -----. Brest
    In consequence of the numerous prizes sold at Brest, various articles can be bought for the United States at advantageous prices; offers to transact these purchases.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 4; L.S. 1p.; Cuchet, Gaspard-Joseph. Paris
    Sending him Faujas de Saint-Fond's "Recherches sur les volcano Éteints du Vivarais et du Velay," for which he subscribed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Speaks of the Marquis de la Fayette in the most complimentary manner. Commends Count d'Estaing highly, and explains the cause for the ungrounded prejudice against him; the peaceable, inoffensive and courteous behaviour of his men. Proposed invasion of Canada.
    Bibliography
    Printed in works (Sparks, VIII, 305).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Courcelle, ----- de. Paris
    Thanks Franklin for his kindness to M. Briffant who has been well recieved in Boston and asks that the enclosed letter be forwarded to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Precautions taken before recommending M. Jean de Neufville to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 5; A.L.S. 9p.; Bingham, William. St Pierre
    Arrival of Comte d'Estaing and his fleet. Damage sustained by Admiral Byron's fleet during a storm. Capture of the Island of St. Lucia by the English; the expedition against them of Comte d'Estaing, and its ignominious failure, owing to the Comte's weakness and cowardice. Encloses an extract of a letter to M. de Sartine from the Governor of Guadeloupe, on behalf of the owners and crew of an American privateer which was unfortunately sunk by one of the batteries of that island.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Roberdeau, Daniel. Philadelphia
    Requesting Franklin to forward the enclosed letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Bradford, Jno. Boston
    Introducing his son to Franklin, and asking him to afford the young man his patronage and advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 6; L.S. 3p.; Calmels, -----. Brest
    Encloses a list of certain articles which he offers to procure for the United States. Details relative to the sale of "La Revanche."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Holtzer, Antoine. Colmar
    Concerning a new quality of beer and its various excellencies.
  - to The [American] Commissioners., 1779 January 7; L.S. John Lloyd et al. 5p.; John Lloyd, et al., Merchants. Nantes
    Complaining of lack of protection to American vessels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 8; L.S. 1p.; Calmels, -----. Brest
    Has just procured an inventory of the sale of the two ships; believes that the larger of the two vessels will be suitable to Franklin's purpose, as well as the cargo of merchandise.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 Jan. 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Introducing the Baron Sturler de l'Altemberg.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 8 and February 26; Mem. in 3d P. 1p.; Dagord, Vincent
    Asks him to obtain his deliverance from prison so as to enter the service of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 9; A.L.S. 4p.; Reiche, Rev. Paul Christopher
    A Lutheran clergyman with a large family, desires to go to America and earn his living. Has supported his family by teaching, preaching and writing books. Wishes to know whether he can make a support by teaching writing or farming in America; if these are impossible, suggests aiding the American army by his knowledge of strategy.
    (In Latin.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Greenleaf, Joseph. Boston
    Writes on behalf of his son who has been a prisoner in Portsmouth Jail for several months; begs Franklin to procure his exchange and, if possible, send him home in some public vessel.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 9; A.L.S. 5p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Concerning the depreciation of the currency and the consequent high prices. Danger of contracting debts in the present reduced state of the paper credit. Possibility of France advancing a sufficient sum to sink the Continental paper. Aid he has given to two Americans who were wounded in an engagement with an English privateer. The "Governor Livingston" and the "Chasseur" almost ready to sail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Holtzendorff, Louis-Casimir, baron de
    Sends copies of General Washington's letter, testifying to his good character, also his congé from General Gates; joins to this his general essay on the Prossian Tactics which he proposed to General Washington when he found that the American officers were in need of learning their métier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Collas, Peter. Nantes
    Thanking Franklin for his favor received by Mr. Wharton, as well as for the articles therein mentioned. According to his advice, has written to Mrs. Mecom for directions how to make crown soap.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Montboissier, Philippe-Claude de Beaufort-Canillac, comte de. Paris
    Reminding Franklin of his promise to give a letter of recommendation to M. Fleurian de Langle, a relative of the Marquis de la Fayette.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 12; A.L.S. 6p.; Soller, -----. Saarlouis
    Concerning the articles manufactured in his iron foundry, and the prices.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Affairs in Holland; quotes an explanation of France's memoir, sent to the Grand Pensionnaire by the French Ambassador.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    His project of going to America checked; one of the richest ships to his address has been blown up; every soul perished and not a farthing saved; loss sustained by M. de Chaumont and M. de Montieu.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 12; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Jeffries, Dr. John. London
    Assurance of the continued love and esteem of the members of their Society for Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Lanthenar, François. Lyons
    Explaining a project of himself and a friend to go to America and engage in commerce at first, and later in agriculture; begs Franklin to give them his advice, and if possible, facilitate their passage over.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Maire de Gimel, Jacques
    Announcing the burning of the ship "le Flaman," Captain Blondeau. Has written many times requesting answers to his letters he brought from the Governor of Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Ludwig, Georg Balthasar. Amstadt
    Offers to send woolen clothes to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Sayre, Stephen. Copenhagen
    Acknowledging his letter of the 25th ult. Containing the approval of his proposition; unfortunately, before its receipt, the ship intended for the voyage was sold at public auction; his regret at such a miscarriage of his plans. His intended trip to Stockholm; is aware that America does not need the good will of any more European powers, but nothing ought to be neglected. Mr. F. Lewis has promised his utmost interest to get him some employment in Europe; his present character that of a modern Don Quixote.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Lavabre, Doerner and Co. Paris
    Concerning an order by Franklin, to pay a certain sum to a young man, named Colomb de Nismes, at present in a Savannish regiment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    His Mecca is to see Franklin in Holland, consummating the work begun by himself.
  - to Sartine, 1779 January 15; L.S. 2p.; D' Arbaud, Helle Comte. Basse Terre
    Regarding the indemnification demanded for the owner and crew of the "Fair Play."
    (Copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Price, Richard, 1723-1791
    Begging F[rankli]n to procure for the bearer, Mr. Morris, access to the persons he wants to see; his business is to procure some passports; trusts this will give Dr. Franklin small trouble. Sends the enclosed papers by Mr. Morris, of their contents he is ignorant.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Pommereuille, -----, sieur de. Paris
    Undaunted by the cruelty of the English toward French prisoners, desires to fight under the colors of liberty; begs for an interview so that, should his request be refused, he may still have seen the most illustrious man of his age.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Pickerin, Capt Thomas. Brest
    Concerning the two prizes taken by him since he left Brest; the Court of Admiralty's failure to condemn the cargo of the second prize.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    By a memoir just presented, Holland is excluded from all the favors which France grants to neutral nations; Amsterdam alone to be left in enjoyment of these; great discontent prevails.
    In French.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Sends Franklin two of his chapters; takes the liberty of keeping the third for himself. Impatiently awaiting the arrival of M. de Montieu.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Aigueville ----- d’. Alicante
    Orders from the King of Spain to admit American corsairs and their prizes to the port of Alicante; necessity of having a consul-general there to look after American interests; offers himself for the position.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Lemire, -----. Dieppe
    Enclosing à memorandum of the sale of two small prizes. Informing Franklin of some excellent beer and rum which he can purchase.
  - to Franklin and Lee., 1779 January 17; L.S. 2p.; John Watson and John Swain. Calais
    Acquainting them with their capture, by the English, in October, 1777, their subsequent escape, and present confinement in Calais prison; their destitute condition and desire to obtain their freedom in order to reënter the American service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779?] June 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Chardon, Daniel-Marc-Antoine. Paris
    Informing Franklin that the affair of Captain Macknil [McNeill] has been tried and settled in the Captain's favor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Nicolas, Pierre-François. Paris
    Has sent him a copy of his work "Dissertation Chimique sur leseaux minérales de la Lorraine"; stimulating effect on his own work of Franklin's treatise on electricity. Has discovered a sure process of dyeing cottons a fast black; offers to treat with Franklin concerning this discovery, if it can be of use to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 19; A.L.S. 1p.; La Blancherie, Claude-Mammès de Pahin Champlain de
    Sends Franklin the new plan of the institution of which he is the head; invites Franklin, his grandson and Dr. Adams to the first meeting, to be held on the 20th inst.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    At the request of Prince Gallitzin, sends him a letter, concerning some experiments in electricity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Gillon, Alexander. Brest
    Begging Franklin to communicate the contents of the enclosed to his colleagues, particularly to Mr. Izard.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    The 26th of January appointed by the King of France for the publication of the new regulations, In case he does not receive a suitable reply from Holland before that time; irresolution in the Holland Assembly; courier sent to France to request a week's delay; attitude of Amsterdam.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Begging Franklin to pay no attention to an open letter which may be presented to him by a M. Poirier, a lawyer of Dunkirk; his reasons for doubting the good faith of this gentleman; his desire to obtain the position of American agent at Dunkirk; is sending Franklin four lines by the hand of a much better friend to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 20; D. 1p.; Walton, Lieut Thomas. Spithead
    Copy of discharge given to William Gardner an American prisoner on board the British warship, "Lenox."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Ford, Hezekiah. Chaillot
    Is quite sure that he left the papers containing the Resolves of Congress in Franklin's book at Passy, after he had finished the copy for Mr. Lee; if they are not to be found will send Franklin a fair copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Monthuley, -----. Evreux
    Having heard that Franklin was pleased with his samples of two colored cloths, offers him the fruits of his labors. Encloses a letter for Mr. Williams.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Holtzendorff, Louis-Casimir, baron de. Paris
    Wishes to know if Franklin has conferred with his colleagues respecting the papers he sent him and their decision.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Izard, Ralph. Paris
    Calls upon Franklin to fulfil his promise, made in the presence of Lee and Adams, to send him a copy of his answer to the writer's letter of the 2d inst.; desires at the same time all his reasons, in writing, for disobeying the Resolution of Congress of May 7th, 1778.
  - to Fizeaux, 1779 January 21; A.L.S. 4p.; Capellen tot den Pol, Joan Derk van der
    Despairs of making any progress in favor of American credit, while false reports of English victories are being continually circulated; urges the wisdom of having a correspondent devoted to the interests of France and America, to whom authentic reports might be forwarded. Favorable impression created by Governor Trumbull's letter. Appreciates the honor done him by the Ministers at Passy, in their generous commendation of his conduct with regard to the Scottish Brigade; thanks them for their very kind offer, which at present he is unable to accept. Excellent choice France has made in the person of the Duc de la Vauguyon.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 21; A.L.S. 4p.; Lloyd, John et al. American Merchants at Nantes. Nantes
    Concerning a convoy to guard merchant ships to America. Severity of weather hinders sailing of ships. Acknowledge receipt of a copy of the Treaty of Commerce, and ask what ports are to be free, pursuant to the 30th Article. Refer to danger from Barbary corsairs, and ask advice as to protection from them. Pray for more knowledge as to the impost duties levied by each of the United States. Patience and perseverance will win the present contest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Parny des Salines, ----- de. Paris
    Writes for information concerning a sum of money deposited in the public treasury, at Charleston, and redeemable at a certain date.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Gilbank, Jno. Nantes
    The mortification of their refusal to accept his bill; there is one method still left by which he may raise the desired sum; that is, for them to endorse a bill drawn by him on the President of Congress; if this suggestion is also refused, is afraid it will be attributed to their indifference to the fate of an American officer. Complains bitterly of the treatment he has received; exonerates Congress from being privy to it; hints at a time coming when he may be able to resent this treatment in another way than by words.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 21; L.S. 1p.; George Hakins, John Tomling, James Horel, John Redaway and John Sheay. Quimper
    Their escape from a British privateer and their present imprisonment among a parcel of French thieves, with only six sons a day to live upon, to lie on dirt at night, and to gaze through iron bars all day; beg Franklin to take pity on his poor countrymen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 22; L.S. 4p.; Thompson, John. Brest
    Was appointed gunner on the brig "Lexington." Lost a leg while on that vessel. Has been in the Royal Marine Hospital at Brest. Is now cured from the effects of an operation. Wishes to proceed to America and requests a passage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Adamoli, -----. Paris
    Sending Franklin a poem which he trusts will meet with his approbation. Desires to know if the "Société d'Emulation," of London, rewards discoveries presented by any but Englishmen; the discovery in question will considerably shorten long and difficult calculations in weights, measures, monies, etc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 22; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Criticised for her informal relations with Franklin; necessary to submit to what is called propriety. State of her nerves; begs him to drink tea with her every day.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Nov., 1906, 168.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Niles, Robert. Nantes
    Was captured by a Jersey privateer whose captain accidentally let fall that Mr. Dobrée, of Guernsey, was one of his owners; his son, Mr. Dobree of Nantes, anxious to have in writing the particulars of this conversation, but as it is a matter which concerns the country, thought it best to leave the decision with them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David
    For his sentiments, refers Franklin to his letters written as a Member of Parliament to his constituents. The alliance between France and the United States is an obstacle to peace.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 312; Bigelow, VI, 296).
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 January 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning some property belonging to Mr.Simeon Deane which was delivered by mistake to M.Schweighauser. Bill for gunstocks, etc.
  - to The American Commissioners, 1779 January 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Lee, William. Frankfort
    Requesting the Commissioners to obtain articles of war for the State of Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Girard, -----Rennes
    Demands justice from Franklin in the case of one of his compatriots, who hired a chaise from him on the pretext of going to Paris to consult him on important business; since then nothing has been heard of the chaise.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
    Has communicated Franklin's favor of January 1st to the Board of Sick and Hurt and received their answer to the effect that measures are being taken to send to France the number of Americans agreed upon for the exchange.
  - to The American Commissioners, 1779 January 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Requesting passes for certain American ships which otherwise are taken by their own people as well as by the enemy. Reports received from Cadiz of an engagement between Comte d'Estaing and an English fleet. Letters from Martinique mention that their ports are blockaded by English cruisers and that Comte d'Estaing is daily expected.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Pommereuille, -----, sieur de. Paris
    Upon hearing that there are 5,000 officers without employment in America, gave up an idea of bearing arms there. Is very anxious to join a friend of his in Boston; desires to know something about that city, if a man can live there pleasantly and if the price of provisions are very high.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Kentisbear, William. Toulon
    Implores Dr. Franklin to procure his freedom, that he might secure a pass and proceed to his family in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Swallow, James. Calais prison
    Begging Franklin to obtain his release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Darrell, Josiah. Nantes